the directory entry has one Dirty Bit
that indicates that the block is dirty
in some cache in the system and for
every cache in the system the directory
entry has one bit that indicates whether
the block is present in that cache if
the presence bit is one for a particular
cache that means that we think that
cache has a copy of the block if the
presence bit is zero that means that we
know for sure that that cach does not
have the Block in a state that is not I
so let's say we have one block caches at
core zero and one and let's say this is
the directory entry for Block B where
this is the Dirty Bit and these are the
presence bits for Cores 0 1 2 3 4 5 6
and 7 so this is an eight core system so
we need eight bits to represent presence
of the Block in the caches initially the
block is not dirty and is not present in
any of the caches let's say that core
zero reads From the Block B the block is
not in its cache so it's treated like
it's in the invalid State we put the
read request out normally this read
request would be put out on the bus and
because no other cache has this the
memory would respond but now we don't
have snooping anymore so all requests
for a block would be sent first first to
the home slice of the block and we
determine what is the Home Slice by
looking at the address of the block
different blocks are distributed among
different slices so that we get an even
load between the slices so let's say we
determine that for Block B this is the
slice where we go and once the request
gets there we look at the directory
entry for it the directory entry says
that the block is not anywhere in the
system so now we can get get the data
from memory and send the data back to
the cach zero and we need to tell the
cach zero everything that the bus would
normally tell it so we tell it that it
has exclusive access because there are
no other sharers and we give it the data
that response gets back to cach zero and
now if it has the exclusive state it can
put the Block in that state and put the
data for B here when the directory sends
the data to cach Z it changes is the
presence bit for that cache to one also
we sent the data with exclusive access
if cach Z modifies the data it doesn't
have to notify the directory back so we
also set the Dirty Bit the Dirty Bit
here will not cause a write back it will
cause us to find if a cash needs to do a
right back so now why does this work
better than a bus well because while
cash Zer was doing this with this
directory slice cash one could have done
something like that for another block
with another directory slice completely
independently however if cachan tried to
write to be at about the same time when
read B was occurring we would send a
right request to the same directory
entry and now between these two messages
the directory controller needs to select
one in this case it chose read request
first so officially this read happened
before this right so the core here gets
to read the Block B and only then the
right gets processed by the directory so
when this right request arrives here
again this right request would be placed
on the bus seen by this cache as a
result this cach would invalidate and we
will get the Block in the modified state
with the directory we sent the request
to the directory controller it sees that
the block is present and possibly dirty
in the in this case cach Zero
so what now happens is the directory
forwards the right request for B to the
cashes that are present in this case it
forwards it to cash Z cash Z Now sees
this request just as if it was snooped
from the bus and because it has the data
in the exclusive state it can choose to
respond with the data or it may just
keep quiet and confirm the invalidation
so what happens here is once the right
request has been given to this cachee we
need to send the acknowledgement at
least if not the data to the back to the
directory controller that says that we
are done invalidating our copy so at
this point we have invalidated our copy
when the acknowledgement arrives here
the directory controller can change this
to zero if the data didn't arrive then
we can erase the Dirty Bit And now
because we don't have the data still we
will read the memory and send the data
to cach one and and because we are
acknowledging a write request we again
set a dirty bit and now the presence
Vector gets a one for the bit that
corresponds to cach one and now we get
to set M here and write to the B here so
as you can see this is how the caches
can do their normal coherence but now
instead of everybody seeing everything
that we need to send request to the
directory which then sends out the
messages that need to be sent only to
those caches that actually might have
the block so if a block is shared by
only two cores then we will be only
sending a very few messages in contrast
the bus would force us to basically
broadcast to all of the cores so this
also saves a lot of bandwidth because we
are using point-to-point network links
to send just this meanwhile other cores
could be doing something like this with
another directory entry completely
independently over a network